<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth a treatyse aeynst [sic] pestyle[n]ce [et] of ye infirmities</title>
            <title>Here begynneth a litil boke the whiche traytied many gode thinges for the pestilence.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1511</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4592.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104892</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840622</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840622</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5146</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5146)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1626:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth a treatyse aeynst [sic] pestyle[n]ce [et] of ye infirmities</title>
                  <title>Here begynneth a litil boke the whiche traytied many gode thinges for the pestilence.</title>
                  <author>Joannes Jacobi, d. 1384. Régime de l'épidémie.</author>
                  <author>Knutsson, Bengt, d. 1462, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Mikkelsen, Knud, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Enprynted by Wynkyn de worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1511?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Derived from a Latin translation by Bengt Knutsson of "Régime de l'épidémie" by Joannes Jacobi. The Latin version has been attributed to Knutsson and to Knud Mikkelsen. This English version was originally published ca. 1485 as: Here begynneth a litil boke the whiche traytied many gode thinges for the pestilence.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Plague --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:5146:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5146:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ Here begynneth a treatyſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynſt peſtyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infirmites.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>Ptholomeus.</p>
               <p>Aſtronomye.</p>
               <figDesc>Ptholomeus (or Ptolomy) and a lady study the stars with astrological instruments, an astrolabe and armillary sphere (or spherical astrolabe)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:5146:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the reuerence and worſhyp of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed trynyte &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gloryous virgyn ſaynt ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry / &amp; the conſeruacyon of the comyn wele of cryſten people as well for them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le as for remedy of them that ben ſeke. I the byſſhop of Aruſiens in the royalme of denmark doctour of phyſycke wyll wryte by the mooſt expecte and famous doctours auctoryſed in phyſyque ſome thynges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Infyrmyte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peſtylence whiche day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enfecteth &amp; ſoone ſuffreth vs to departe out of this lyfe. ¶ Fyrſt I wyll wryte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tokenes of this infyrmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / ¶ The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſes wherof it cometh. ¶ The thyrde remedyes for the ſame. ¶ The .uij. comforte for the herte &amp; the pryncypall membres of the body. ¶ The .v. whan it ſhal be ſeaſon to be let blode. Fyrſt I ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tokens of this infyrmyte .vij. thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges ought to be noted in the ſame y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt is whan in a ſommers day the weder oftentymes chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mornyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the weder appereth to rayne / afterwarde it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth cloudy &amp; at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt wynde in the ſouth. The ſecon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de token is whan in ſomer the dayes appereth alder ke &amp; lyke to rayne &amp; yet it rayneth not / and yf many dayes ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue it is to drede grete peſtylence. The thyrde token is whan grete multytude of flyes ben vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe then it is ſygne / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayer is venymous and infecte. The .iiij. token is whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſterres ſemen oftentymes to fal / than it is token y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the ayer is infect w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moche venemous vapours. The .v. token is whan a blaſynge ſterre is ſene in the element aboue / then it ſholde fortune ſone after to be grete manſlaughter. in batayll. The .vi. token is wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is grete lyght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge &amp; thundre namely out of the ſouth. The .vij. to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:5146:2"/>is whan grete wyndes paſſen oute of the ſouth / they be foule &amp; vnclene / therfore whan theſe tokens appere it is do drede grete peſtylence but god of his mercy wyll remeue it. Theſe thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges folowynge ben the cauſes of peſtylence. Thepeſtyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce cometh of .iiij. thynges / ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme it cometh fro the rote byneth other whyle fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rote aboue to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may fele ſenſibly how the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of the ayer appereth vnto vs / &amp; ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme it cometh of both togyder as well. fro the rote aboue as fro the rote byneth / as we ſee a ſege or a preuy nexte to a chamber or of ony other pertyculer thynge why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che corrupteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayer in his ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; qualyte whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is a thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge may happe euery day / &amp; therof cometh the ague of peſtylence / &amp; aboute the ſame many phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycyons be deceyued / not ſuppoſynge this axes to be a peſtylence / ſomtyme it cometh of dede careyn or cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupcion of ſtandynge water in dyches or ſloughes &amp; other corrupt places / and theſe thynges ſomtyme be vnyuerſall &amp; ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme perticuler. ¶ Fro the rote aboue it fortuneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſes of the bodyes aboue the ayer by whome the ſpyryte of lyfe is corrupt in man or beeſt as Auice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſayth in his .iiij. boke / by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of thayr aboue the bodyes byneth lyghtly be infect / for thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſyons aboue corrupteth the ayer &amp; ſo the ſpirytes of man be corrupt / this infyrmyte cometh from the rote aboue / &amp; bynethe whan of thynpreſſyons aboue the ayer is corrupte / and of the putryfaccyon or ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten carcyne / or of vyle places byneth an infyrmyte is called in a man / or ſuch an Infyrmyte ſomtyme is an axes / ſomtyme a poſtome or a ſwelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and that is in many thynges. Alſo the ayer inſpyred ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme is
<pb facs="tcp:5146:3"/>venymous and corrupt / hurtynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herte / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nature many wayes is greued ſoo / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he perceyueth not his harme for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyrgyn appereth fayre &amp; ſheweth good dygeſtyon yet neuertheleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pacyent is lyke to dye / wherfore many phyſycyens ſeynge the vryn of theyr pacyentes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpeke ſuperfycyally &amp; be deceyued. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is nede that euery pacyent proue to hym ſelfe a good &amp; experte phyſycyen. Theſe thynges wryten be fore are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſes of peſtylence. But aboute theſe thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges two queſtyons be moeued. The fyrſt is wherfore one dyeth &amp; a nother dyeth not in a towne where me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be dede in one houſe / &amp; in a nother houſe there dyeth none. The ſeconde queſtyon is whether peſtylence ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagyous. To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt queſtyon I ſaye it may happe to be of tho cauſes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that ſuffreth / an example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that doth / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Influence of the bodyes aboue behol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth that place or that place more than this place or this place / &amp; the pacyent is more diſpoſed to dye tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another. therfore it is to be noted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodyes be more hote dyſpoſed of open pore than bodyes Infect ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge the poores ſtopped w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many humoures where bodyes be of reſolucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or openynge / as men whiche abuſen them ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> women or vſe often tymes ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes / or men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be hote w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> laboure or grete anger they haue theyr bodyes more diſpoſed to this grete ſeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. To the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de queſtyon I ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> peſtylence ſores be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagyous by cauſe of infect humoures of bodyes and thereke or ſmoke of ſuche ſoores is venymous and corrupteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayer &amp; therfore it is to flee for ſuche perſones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be infect / in peſtylence tyme no dody ſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſtande in grete prece of people by cauſe ſome man
<pb facs="tcp:5146:3"/>of them may be infect. Therfore wyſe phyſycyens in vyſyty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſeke folke ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ferre fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paciente holdyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge their face towarde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dore or wy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dowe. And ſo ſhol de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of ſeke folke ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. And it is good to a pacyent euery daye, for to chaunge his chamber / &amp; to haue the wyndowe open ayenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> northe &amp; eeſt / &amp; to ſpere the wyndowes ayenſt the ſouth / for the ſouth wynde hath two cauſes of putryfycacyon. The fyrſt is it maketh a man beynde hole or ſeke feble in theyr bodyes. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de cauſe is as wryten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde of Amphyroſmis y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouth wynde greueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heerynge &amp; hurteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herte bycauſe it openeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poores of man and entreth in to the herte / wherfore it is good to an hole man in tyme of peſtylence whan the winde is in the ſouth to be within the houſe all day &amp; yf it ſhal be nede a man to go out / yet let hym abyde in the houſe tyll the ſonne be vp in the eeſt paſſynge ſouthe warde ¶ The remedyes of peſtylence here after foloweth. Now it is to wete by what remedyes a man may pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue hym ſelfe fro peſtylence / fyrſt ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrytynge of Ieremye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ought to forſake euyll thynges &amp; do good dedes &amp; mekely to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe his ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / for why it is the hyeſt remedy in tyme of peſtyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; confeſſyon to be preferred of other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycynes. Neuertheleſſe I promytte you verely it is a good remedy to voyde &amp; chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thynfect places. but ſome may not prouffytably chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge their places / ther fore as moche as to them is poſſible it is to eſchewe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery cauſe of putryfaccion / &amp; namely euery fleſſhely luſte with women is to be eſchewed Alſo the ſothern wynde whyche is naturally enfecteth therfore ſpere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyndowes ayenſt the ſouth as it is ſayd before vn
<pb facs="tcp:5146:4"/>to the fyrſte houre after the myddes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye. Then open y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyndowes ayenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> north. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame cauſe euery foule ſtynche is to be eſchewed / of ſtabyll ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge feldes wayes or ſtretes / &amp; namely of ſtynky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge dede carayne &amp; mooſt of ſtynky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge watres where in many places water is kepte by .vij. dayes or .ij. nygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / or elles there be gutters of water caſten vnder the erthe whiche cauſeth grete ſtynke &amp; corrupcyon &amp; of this cauſe ſome deye in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> houſe where ſuche thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ges happen / &amp; in a nother houſe dye none as it is ſaid before. lyke wiſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place where be wurtes &amp; coles pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trefyed it maketh a noyfull ſauoure &amp; ſtynkynge for as by the ſwete odoure of bawme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> herte &amp; the ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes haue recreacion / ſo of euyll ſauours they be made feble wherfore kepe youre houſe that an infect ayer enter not in / for an Infect ayer mooſt cauſeth putry faccyon in places and houſes where folke ſlepe / ther fore lette youre houſe be clene and make clere fyre of wood fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge / let your houſe be made with fumy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacyon of herbes / that is to ſaye with leues of baye tre Ieneper vberyorgany it is in thappotycary ſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes / wormwode rewe mugworte &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">c</hi> tre of aloes whiche is beſt but it is dere. Suche a fumy taken by the mouche &amp; eres openeth thynwarde partes of the body. Alſo it is teſchewe all grete repleccyons by cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe full bodyes by lyghtly infect / as Auice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſayth in the fourth canon / they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chargen theyr bodyes with reſpeccion / ſhorten theyr lyfe. Alſo comyn bathes are to be eſchewed / for alytell cruſt corrupteth all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body Thefrore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people as moche as is poſſyble is to be eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chewed / leeſt of infect brethes ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be infect / but whan the multytude of people may not be eſchewed.
<pb facs="tcp:5146:4"/>then vſe the remedyes folowynge. In the mornynge whan ye ryſe / waſſhe a lytell rewe &amp; one or two fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berde nottes clene w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſalte &amp; ete them / &amp; yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can not be had than ete brede or a toſte ſopped in veneger na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely in troublous and cloudy weder. Alſo i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyme of peſtylence it is better to abyde win the houſe / for it is not holſome to go in to cyte or towne / alſo let your houſe be ſprynkled ſpecyally in ſomer with vyneger and roſes &amp; with leues of vyne tree. Alſo it is good to waſſhe your handes ofte tymes in the day w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; veneger / &amp; wype your face with your handes &amp; ſmell to them. Alſo it is good alwaye to ſauoure ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger thynges. In the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of peſſane I myght not eſchewe the company of people for I wente for hous to houſe bycauſe of my pouerte to cure ſeke folkes / therfore brede or a ſponge ſopped in vyneger I toke with the holdynge it to my mouth and noſe bycauſe all egre thynges ſtoppen the wayes of humours and ſuffreth no venymous thynges to entre in to a man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes body &amp; ſo Ieſcaped the peſtylens my felowes ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſholde not lyue / theſe thynges I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued by my ſelfe. ¶ Here foloweth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryncypall membres. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> her te be theſe / ſaffron auiſex plantayn: w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other herbes they open the inwarde ſpyryte / &amp; theſe be good amon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the comyn people where lyghtly it happeneth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on is inefete of another therfore be ware the brethe of a nother. Alſo of an Infect ayer a mans eyen be made dymme yf he bere not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forſayd thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges in his hande Alſo it is holſome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye waſſhe your mouth face eien &amp; handes oftentymes in the day w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> roſe water medeled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> veneger / &amp; yf ye haue no roſe water take veneger
<pb facs="tcp:5146:5"/>and ſo theſe thynges vſed ye may go ſurely amonge the people. Alſo a naturall lax of the bely is a grete re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medy elles prouoke a lax be a ſuppoſory craftly / vſe pypylle peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciales for they be good / they be in thap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>potycarye ſhoppes. Alſo kepe fyre alway in your hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe for it letteth moche the Impreſſyons of the bodyes aboue &amp; clarefyeth the ayer. Alſo it is profytable as well for &amp; hole ſeke folkes to drynke tryarle therfore take it .ij. rymes a day with clene wyne limphat or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> clere roſe water or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> clere ale / take a quantyte of trya<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cle &amp; two ſponefull of clere wyne or roſe water or ale dyſſoiue the tryacle in the cup &amp; dry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke it &amp; dyne not tyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myddes of the day y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the tryacle may haue his operacyon / then cheſe a good dyſſhe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mete / &amp; dry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke clere wyne &amp; often tymes drynke in the day but not moche togyder / for moche hadoundaunce of drynke putryfyeth the humours. Alſo beware hote thynges in metes as peper &amp; garlyke / though peper purgeth the brayne from the flewme &amp; ſpecyally y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> membres from vycyous humours / yet it maketh moche hete / &amp; hete falleth in to putryfaccion / bytternes onely is mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re pleaſe than hote odoure or ſauoure. Alſo garlyke though it purgeth flewine &amp; put out all humours &amp; prouoketh an appetyte to ete &amp; ſuffreth no drye ayer to entre yet it troubleth the eyen &amp; maketh the hede hote therfore it is not good to ete garlyk. The peſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence groweth often tymes of an hote cauſe therfore all metes the more they be lyght dygeſtion ſo moche they be the better / In the mornynge ete boyled mete at euyn roſted / forbere brothe &amp; potage w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out they be eyger / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of this ſekenes eyger meters be bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other. Alſo for bere all fruytes but yf they
<pb facs="tcp:5146:5"/>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyger / as cheryes or pome garnates or a lytell of a pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re or apple by the way of medycyne / bycauſe all fruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te enduceth putryfacryon / ete conuenyent ſpyces as gy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ſynamum comyn macys &amp; ſaffro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / theſe be the beſt ſauce may be made for ryche people / for poore ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke rewe ſage fyllberde nottes percely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> veneger my<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te togyder theſe be good &amp; letteth putryfaccyon. To be mery in his herte is a grete remedy for helth of his body. Therfore in tyme of this grete Infyrmyte he ware ye drede notdeth but lyue merely &amp; hope to ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue longe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ For the lettynge of blode.</head>
               <p>¶ Lettynge of blode ones in the moneth may be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / but age or other thynges forbede it as pylgryms or feble ꝑfones y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haue the flyxe / ſuffre to be let blode in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayne called baſilica on the ryght or lyft ſyde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ety<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / &amp; after inciſion of the baſiliſca be mery &amp; drynke wyne or ale temperatly / ſlepe not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> day wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baſilica is but / yf ye ſele you greued to be infect / than eſchewe ſlepe &amp; be walkynge &amp; moeuynge / for by ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe thynwarde hete induceth poyſon to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herte and to other ſpecyall membres / ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnneth ony herbe may take away ſuche poyſon / whiche ſholde not be yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wolde be moeuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to &amp; fro / but ſome wolde ſaye wherfore ſholde flepe be eſchewed / I ſaye ſhortely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in peſtylence tyme anone after mete yf a body lyſt to ſlepe / then ſuche a luſt ought to be forborne by a ſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce walky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in the gardyns or feldes / &amp; therfore Aui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenne wryteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yf a man wolde ſlepe he muſt dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a good draught of ale or wyne a fore / bycauſe a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beynge a ſlepe draweth many humours / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuyl hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mours be put doune by thumours of a good draught. But ſome wolde vnderſtonde how man a may felt
<pb facs="tcp:5146:6"/>whan he is infect / I ſay that a man whiche is infect y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day he eteth not moche mete / for he is replenyſſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euyll homours / &amp; forth with after dyner he hathe luſte to ſlepe &amp; feleth grete hete vnder colde. Alſo he hath grete payne in the forhede but all theſe thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges he may put away by moeuynge of a place hyder and theder to ryde or to walke he may not for ſlouth / of the body &amp; the weyght of the ſame. Alſo a man whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is infect hath luſt to ſlepe euery houre for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myn w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the body troubleth the ſpyryte of lyfe ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alway he wolde reſt &amp; ſlepe &amp; ſo of theſe tokens a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall knowe &amp; fele hym ſelfe infect / &amp; yf a body wyll not beleue this. Abyde the myddes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day / &amp; then anone he ſhall fele a ſwelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vnder the arme aboute the ſhare / or aboute the eres &amp; therfore ſe an hye &amp; a good medycyne / forbere ſlepe bycauſe of the thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges aforeſayd / &amp; it is playne that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpyryte of lyfe reſteth in ſlepe &amp; all the body here and there is venymed. All theſe thinges I haue proued by my ſelfe / theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges knowen whan a man feleth hym felfe infect as ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne as he may let hym be let blode plenteuouſly tyl he ſwoune / then ſtoppe the vayne / for a lytell letynge of blode moeueth or ſtyreth vemyn / yf a man wyll not haue many vaynes kut togyder / then let hym ſuffre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayne kut to renne tyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blode w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> drawe / for alytell bledy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge meueth ſtrongly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> venym as it is ſayd afore alſo a man whether he be infect or not yf he be let blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de let hym forbere ſiepe all that day tyll mydnyght fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / &amp; alway let blode y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayne vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyde of the body where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge appereth. Therfore yf a ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge appere vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght arme let blode in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame arme in the vayne called medtana / yf it
<pb facs="tcp:5146:6"/>be ryſen. But &amp; yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he fele ony ſuche ſwelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge after his ſlepe / thenne vpon the contrarye parte the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of bloode muſte be made / as for yf the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge or ryſynge appere in the ryghte arme lette hym bolde in the lyfte arme in epate or (baſilica) or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana. And yf that a ſwellynge or a moeuynge appere vnder the lefte arme lette hym bloode in the ryghte arme lyke wyſe as it be forſayd of the lyfte arme / and ſoo of all other places of the body / lette bloode on the contrarye parte of ſuche ſwellynge or ryſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. And that the lettynge of bloode be veraye lytell and feble / Thenne lette the pacyente ſlepe after the myddes of the daye / and thenne alwaye within the myddes of the daye / for he muſte be in contynuelly meuynge rydynge or goynge moderatly / and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde yf that the ſwellynge growe lette hym not be a frayde of dethe by cauſe ſuche a ſwelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge putteth oute all maner of euylles / and maketh a man veray hole. And that the ſooner a ſwellynge may be made type / take this medycyne as foloweth. Bruſe the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of an elder tree the whiche ben fayre and grete and putte therto muſtarde the whiche ſhall be well and ſtrongely grounden in a payre of quernes / and then whan ye haue done as I haue tolde you / take and dryue a playſter of the forſayd thynges good &amp; thyche and after put it vpon the ſore and ſwellynge and it ſhall aledge hym anone of the forſayd ſykenes ¶ Alſo for the forſayd ſwellynge / or ryſynge in the necke / or in the arme / or mony other place of a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes body whan it appereth take fylberde nottes fyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and rewe and bruſe theym togyder in a morter well and laye it vpon the ſwellynge. And yf that it
<pb facs="tcp:5146:7"/>appere vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> left arme let hym blode in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myddes of the ſame or i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuer whiche is aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lytell fynger / &amp; yf it be about the ſhare lete hym blode aboute the here vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſyde / yf the ſwelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge be in the necke let hym blode in the vayne called cepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica about the thombe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hande in the ſame ſyde or in the vayne called medſana of the ſame arme or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hande of the ſame ſyde aboute the lytell fynger / yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwellynge appere aboute the ere let hym blode in the vayne called cephalica of the ſame ſyde or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vayn whiche is betwene the longe fynger and the thombe / leſt many venymous thynges go in to the brayn / or let blode the vayne whiche is aboute the lytell fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is named by phyſycyons baſilica / &amp; yf a ſwelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge appere in the ſholders leſſe it with ventoſyte and fyrſt leſt the vayne called mediana / yf the ſwellyngs be on the backe / leſſe it vpon the vayne called (pidia magna) &amp; all theſe thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges be made yf man ſlepe not before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. ſome ſurgeons wyl put treacle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwellynge But do not ſo / for tryacle putteth out venym. Therfore dry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke tryacle for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> put teth out the ſame. Alſo there is another medycyne ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ſyngrene hylworte other wyſe called wylde tyme mawdelyn graſſe plantayne and a lytell rye floure &amp; breke all theſe togyder tyll yeſe water come out ther of / medle y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> water w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> womans mylke &amp; gyue it to the pacyent faſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge before ſlepe &amp; wyll werke the better for to remeue the ſwelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. Theſe redmeyes be ſuffy cyent to eſchewe this grete ſekeneſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the helpe of god to whom be euer laſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge laude &amp; prayſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out ende. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Enprynted by Wynkyn de worde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5146:7"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
